Guide to the Acton Visual Materials at La Pietra MSS.LaPietra.001
Villa La Pietra
The Acton Photograph Archive
1907-1980
1870-1994
Villa La Pietra
Acton family
MSS.LaPietra.001
100.0 Linear feet
The visual material in this Archive relates to the lives of the Acton family: Arthur Acton (1873-1953), his wife Hortense Mitchell (1871-1962), and their two sons Harold (1904-1994) and William (1906-1945). These loose photographs, photograph albums, negatives, scrapbooks, postcards, as well as images on glass, had been stored by the family at random in boxes, files, drawers, cupboards, desks, hat boxes, etc. in various rooms of their residence Villa La Pietra, Florence (much of it mixed with correspondence and other papers) from around 1903 up until Harold Acton's death in 1994. The Archive includes remarkably fine early studio portraits, many cabinet card photos bearing an albumen or gelatin silver print taken at the end of the 19th century for the Mitchell family and their circle in Chicago, and some cartes-de-visite photos dating from circa 1870 of Arthur Acton's ancestors. There is a very full documentation of the Acton family's life at Villa La Pietra, including visitors to the villa, from the first years of the 20th century up to Harold's death. This is of particular interest as a documentation of the Anglo-American resident community in Florence. Travels taken in Europe and America during this time by members of the family are also well illustrated. There are numerous photographs of Harold Acton's famous circle of friends at Oxford in the 1920s. A valuable series of photographs of China and actors from the Peking Opera survive from the 1930s when Harold lived and taught in Beijing. There is also a complete documentation of the various phases of the Actons' construction of the garden of Villa La Pietra and their work on it from the very first years. Another series of photos show how the interior of Villa La Pietra has appeared over the decades, and document the various works of art which decorate the rooms or have done so in the past. Other photographs of works of art document private collections in the early 20th century, many of which have since been broken up. There are numerous photographs of works of art, purchased by the Actons for study purposes. Other photographs are of places (all over the world), and there is a particularly rich collection of images of Italian villas and gardens in Florence and Tuscany. The collection of postcards (excepting those with correspondence which have been extracted for the paper archives) is very extensive and includes many annotated on the verso documenting travels by Hortense or Harold in the first decades of the 20th century. The valuable collection of glass stereographs and autochromes includes numerous images of the family at Villa La Pietra and its garden. Professional photographs of the family in Florence include works by Nunes Vais and Cecil Beaton. There is a series of photographs of Villa Passerini in Florence, owned by Hortense Mitchell's brother Guy, dating from the first decades of the 20th century by Giuseppe and Vittorio Jacquier. There are also photographs of places in Italy by Carlo Naya (died 1882) and Giorgio Sommer (died 1914). The number of items in the Acton Photograph Archive, including positives and negatives and images on glass (but excluding postcards) is circa 16,700. Restrictions Apply. Please see the Administrative Information section for more details.
Provenance
The visual material in this collection had been stored by the Acton family at random in various rooms of their residence, Villa la Pietra, Florence from around 1903 to the death of the last member of the family, Harold, in 1994. Some of it was mixed up with correspondence and other papers. Much of it lacked dating and identification. It was processed and given a Finding Aid in 2002-2005 by NYU with the help of a grant from the Gladys Krieble Delmas Foundation of New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions. Please note that some items may not be available for consultation at the discretion of NYU for conservation reasons.
Scope and Contents
Note: for the arrangement in albums or boxes, see below in 'Arrangement'. The four members of the Acton family are abbreviated as follows: AA (Arthur Acton), HMA (Hortense Mitchell Acton), HA (Harold Acton) and WA (William Acton).
The collection is arranged into 10 series (and numerous subseries):
Series I: The Actons
Series II: Villa La Pietra
Series III: Family Albums and Scrapbooks
Series IV: Works of Art
Series V: Places
Series VI: Postcards
Series VII: Harold Acton in China and the Far East
Series VIII: Images on glass
Series IX: Glass negatives (10 x 15 cm and over)
Series X: Reali glass negatives
Series I: THE ACTONS
A. Acton, Arthur (I.A.1.-I.A.6.)
(Album 1-3)
Includes prints dating from the early 1900s, some of them cabinet card photographs and studio portraits, also of AA in his apartment and studios in New York and Firenze. There are very early prints of AA in the grounds of Villa La Pietra before the gardens were laid out, and others taken over the years of him alone or with friends in the gardens (and a few of him in the interior of Villa La Pietra). The series showing him with others or of his friends include some taken at Florentine villas, and there are others of vintage cars.
1. alone: Includes prints with WA. There are also a few prints without AA of the interiors of his apartments in Firenze, kept here so as not to separate them from the prints taken at the same time showing him in the same place. Also here are a few prints of AA painting, kept here for the same reason (rather than filed in I.A.6.).
2. with Hortense Acton, née Mitchell: For other photographs of AA with the family, see under Harold Acton (I.C.1.-I.C.5).
3. with others: Includes a few prints of AA with WA. There are a few prints here which may not include AA himself, and there may be some small overlap with I.A.4.
4. friends of Arthur and Hortense Acton: Some of the friends here were also painted by AA so may also appear in I.A.6.
5. his relations: Prints of his father Roger Acton in Cairo include some views of Cairo without him, kept here as obviously taken at the same time. For the album of AA's ancestors, see III. A.10.
6. his painting activity: Includes interiors of his studios in New York at the end of the 19th century, and Firenze (early 20th century) as well as portraits of sitters and models posing.
B. Acton, Hortense née Mitchell (I.B.1.-I.B.4.)
(Album 3-5)
Many early cabinet card photos (mostly by Steffens of Chicago) show HMA as a young girl (the earliest one of her alone is securely dated 1891).There are many prints of HMA's early life in the US on family outings and trips with friends, and her Chicago girlhood friends are recorded in numerous fine cabinet card photos. There are a great many oversize prints in this series. There are early prints of HMA in the grounds and gardens of Villa La Pietra.
1. alone: Includes some early (late 19th century) prints of uncertain identification (perhaps sisters or friends of HMA rather than HMA herself).
2. with others: For HMA with AA, see I.A.2., and for HMA with HA (and the family) see I.C.1.-.7. The prints of a trip to the Missions in SW America ca. 1890s includes many prints of buildings and landscapes with no people, kept here since they are part of the same series taken at the same time.
3. her Chicago girlhood friends: Mostly identified as taken by photographers at the end of the 19th century.
4. her relations (the Mitchell family): For her cousin Louise Gaylord's wedding to Walter Dillingham at Villa La Pietra, with HA and WA as pages, see I.C.1. For her brother Guy Mitchell's Villa Passerini, Firenze, see V.A.1., and for the Dillingham's Villa La Pietra in Honolulu, see V.B.4.
C. Acton, Harold (I.C.1.-I.C.16)
(Album 6-12)
Prints of HA arranged by decade include those with his family. Lots of these were taken in the gardens or the interior of Villa La Pietra, but also in the US and elsewhere in the world, including China in the 1930s. Those with guests at Villa La Pietra include numerous Color prints of the 1970s and 1980s of unidentified visitors. Those showing HA at formal ceremonies are nearly all in Italy.
1. 1900s (alone or with one or more members of his family - AA, HMA, and WA)
2. 1910s (alone or with one or more members of his family - AA, HMA, and WA)
Includes prints of HA in the Dillingham wedding at Villa La Pietra (but see also I.C.13.)
3. 1920s (alone or with one or more members of his family - AA, HMA, and WA)
4. 1930s (alone or with one or more members of his family - AA, HMA, and WA)
See also series VII.
5. 1940s (alone or with one or more members of his family - AA, HMA)
6. 1950s (alone or with HMA)
7. 1960s (alone or with HMA)
8. 1970s (alone)
9. 1980s (alone)
10. 1990s (alone)
11. portraits of
12. with others (not at Villa La Pietra)
13. with guests (at Villa La Pietra)
14. at formal ceremonies
15. friends of: Arranged alphabetically rather than chronologically as in the other subseries (unidentified friends are in Series I.E., including Eton or university friends in I.E.9.). In a few instances there may be some overlap here with I.A.4. (such as Cora Antinori). For HA's friends in China see VII.B.1. and VII.B.2.
16. his funeral
D. Acton, William (I.D.1.-I.D.3.)
(Box 13)
Prints of William alone, and with others, some at parties: but those with HA or his parents are filed under the other member of the family.
1. alone (and portraits of): For WA with AA, HMA, and/or HA, see I.A.1., I.B.1., and 1.C.1.-I.C.4.
2. with others
3. his painting activity: Includes an album scrapbook of an exhibition in London. Portraits of identified sitters have been filed alphabetically. For some painted panels by William Acton, see also IV.A.2.
E. Unidentified (I.E.1.-I.E.13.)
(Box 14-15)
These are prints mostly of unidentified Acton family friends or relations, ordered as far as possible by date within the sub-series. The dogs include the Acton family pet dogs often photographed in the gardens of Villa La Pietra. The last two sub-series have been added here as they fit even less well elsewhere in the collection.
1. men
2. women:
Includes women with babies and children.
3. men and women
4. children
5. babies
6. groups:
Includes groups at Villa La Pietra, but without a member of the Acton family.
7. soldiers: For other prints of soldiers see I.E.8.
8. officers in Italy in the First World War at Villa La Pietra and elsewhere in Tuscany
9. Eton or university friends of HA
10. supposed Acton relations
11. supposed Mitchell relations and Chicago girlhood friends of HA
12. dogs
13. photographers' portfolios
Series II: VILLA LA PIETRA
A. The Gardens (II.A.1.-II.A.10.)
(Album 1-10 and Box 11)
The prints of the gardens have been filed by area (always indicated by where the photographer was standing), following the sub-sections of the gardens established by New York University prior to their restoration. The prints have been arranged as far as possible chronologically (although there are many instances in which the date is uncertain). This rule has in a few instances been over-ridden (for example in the Teatrino and Boschetto, Vista dell'Arco) where similar views of areas of the gardens (i.e. 'looking south' or 'looking north') have been filed together. Prints of the statuary have been filed together at the end of each sub-section, and numbered according to the inventory established by New York University prior to restoration on the gardens. Series II.A.10.ii. is a ring-binder with photos of statues in the gardens taken by Anna Marx (1986), duplicates of prints filed in II.A.1-II.A.7. but here given a different inventory number since they are filed separately. For other early prints of the gardens (including some prints of the gardens under construction in the first years of the 20th century), see also I.A.1., I.A.3., I.A.4., III.A.1., III.A.2., III.A.6., and III.B.1. There are numerous Brogi prints commissioned by the Actons in 1927, and others dating from the 1930s.
1. Viale
2. Piazzale: i Corte, ii Parcheggio
3. Vasche: i Terrazza, ii Prima Vasca, iii Scalone, iv Seconda Vasca, v Peristilio della glicine
4. Tempietto and Teatrino: i Tempietto, ii Teatrino
5. Boschetto: i Vista dell'Arco, ii Vista del Duomo, iii Prato ovale, iv Vista del Colosso, v Vialone, vi Pergola delle Rose
6. Giardino Topiario: i Giardino Segreto, ii Vasca di Diana, iii Prato del Cedro
7. Pomario
8. the park before the construction of the gardens
9. the garden statuary, vases, and masques, before their present installation in the gardens
10. Albums of Garden Photos: i. Album 1930s, ii. Garden statues taken by Anna Marx in 1986, iii. Album of photos by Frederic Faust 1930s, iv. Album given to Harold Acton, July 1974, v. Album of Garden photos (gift of Alexander Zielcke)
B. The Interior and The Collection (II.B.1.-II.E.)
(Album 12-33)
1. the rooms with their contents
General views of each room, followed by prints of the contents, object by object. The rooms are numbered and named, following the Conti inventory in Italian, drawn up in December 1995 by Giovanni Conti. This inventory has also been used in the numbering and description of the works of art in each room, without taking into account that since 1995 the inventory has frequently been subject to revision as regards dates and attributions. The information from the Conti inventory appears where possible in italics in the Finding Aid.
2. works of art from the Collection in previous displays
See also II.D. There may be some small overlap with II.B.1.
3. works which were formerly part of the Collection, but whereabouts at present unknown
Arranged by paintings, sculptures, and decorative arts. Includes stolen works, and may include works formerly in villas on the estate (but see also II.C).
4. collection related works of art
These are works of art very similar to those in the Villa La Pietra Collection (and they have been cross-referenced by the processor to the relevant object in II.B.1.). Arranged by interiors, paintings, and sculpture. For some other objects which may be related to works in the Collection, see IV.A.
5. Historic Albums mostly of the interior and works of art at present in the Collection or probably formerly once belonging to it
These consist of: 12 brown canvas-bound albums, mostly with the photographs pasted on to the page, and bearing their original numbers 1-3 and I-IX on the spine; 2 oversize green canvas albums un-numbered on the spine, containing photos numbered with Reali negative numbers 1-98 and 99-200; 1 oversize album, containing Color prints of the interior of Villa La Pietra in carbochrome, 1973.
The 12 brown canvas-bound albums contain prints mostly of the interior of Villa La Pietra and works of art at present in the Collection or probably formerly once belonging to it, but also contain photographs of works of art no longer in the collection, works of art now in Villas on the estate, a few of the Villa La Pietra gardens and statues, and others of works of art illustrating the Actons' activity as collectors.
The two oversize green canvas albums contain photos taken by Reali probably between 1958 and 1964 (and their numbers correspond to the glass negatives of these prints also preserved in Series X).
The pages of the albums have been numbered in pencil by the processor in square brackets to correspond with the detailed description of each album provided on a print-out kept together with the album (and included in the Finding Aid).
The original numbering of the pages and/or photographs in the albums is usually not consecutive but has always also been recorded, and some of these appear to refer to similar numbers on Brogi photographs. Some pages are blank and some photographs are missing.
Many of the photographs were found to be duplicates of those already in the Archive, and so this was noted in the album description, giving the archive number of the duplicate print. 'Duplicates' have been differentiated from 'Near duplicates' - the difference being that a 'near duplicate' is a print from the same negative but cropped slightly differently or printed with a different exposure.
In the albums where the photographs were not pasted on to the page, a few of these were removed and replaced at an unknown time by photocopies, but the great majority of these were removed to the Archive in 2004 (noting on the original the provenance and Historic Album number) and replaced here with Color photocopies of the recto and verso.
The two oversize green canvas albums have photos by Reali not pasted on to the page but the originals have been left here. They are annotated by HA and numbered by him. Again the duplicates and near duplicates have been noted.
6. Interiors taken by Anna Marx, 1986
These are mostly general views of rooms of Villa La Pietra, rather than individual works of art: however when an art object can be seen clearly it has been given its Conti inventory number, which is part of the title proper in Italian (in this case not in italics). Anna Marx photographed most rooms in the Villa except for III, V, VIII, XXVII, XLIV, XLVI, and L. Instead she photographed XXVI (Bagno), and XLIV (Ufficio, called by her the "Stanza della Signora Malesci"), not documented photographically elsewhere in the Archive as well as the Corridoio (XLII) in greater detail than elsewhere in the Archive.
C. The Estate (II.C.1.-II.C.8.)
(Album 34-35, Box 36)
Here are views of the land (the podere) surrounding Villa La Pietra as well as views from and of Villa La Pietra. The images of the exterior and interior of the five villas on the property (Villa Emilia, Villa Natalia, Villa Colletta, Villa Sassetti, and Villa Ulivi) include works of art and historic albums of the villas.
1. The Podere
2. Villa Emilia
3. Villa Natalia
4. Villa Colletta
5. Villa Sassetti
6. Villa Ulivi
7. unidentified
8. Albums of the villas
D. Other Acton properties (II.D.1.-II.D.3.)
(Album 37)
Many of the art objects photographed in these properties were subsequently part of the Collection of Villa La Pietra. Palazzo Guadagni, Firenze has been included here, but only in order to cross-reference it to the photographs of Arthur Acton in his studio in Series I.A.6. Lungarno Guicciardini, Firenze: two of these three photos are identified on the verso as 'Lungarno Guicciardini', and so were processed here, but they appear, instead, to be interiors of Villa Sassetti. Lancaster Gate was a property owned by the Actons in 1928-32. Many of the photographs are annotated by Guy Mitchell, brother of HMA, who was frequently in London between 1928-32 and WA and HA were also presumably there during that period. In these photographs there is a small overlap with II.B.1.
1. Palazzo Guadagni, Firenze see I.A.6.
2. Lungarno Guicciardini, Firenze
3. Lancaster Gate, London
E. Black-and-white negatives (in sheets and rolls), with their prints made in 2005 (II.E.1.-II.E.4)
(Box 38)
These have been kept together since the negatives are on sheets or rolls, which only became legible when a selection of them (eliminating duplicates and the negatives of very poor quality) were printed in 2005. The prints have been processed in the same order as the above subseries in Series II (and so not necessarily in the same order as the negative sheets). Some of these are of special interest as they are not included elsewhere in the Acton Photograph Archive.
1. 175 negatives
2. Villa La Pietra: the gardens
3. Villa La Pietra: the interior and the Collection
4. Villa La Pietra: the Estate
Series III: Family Albums and Scrapbooks
A. Family Albums (III.A.1.-III.A.10.)
(Box 1 and Album 2)
These are historic albums with photographs usually pasted onto the page. The pages of the albums have been numbered in pencil in square brackets by the processor to correspond with the detailed description of each album provided on a print-out kept together with the album (but not included in full in the Finding Aid).
1. 1903-1905
1a. [1905-1910]
2. 1910-1916
3. 1915-1918
4. 1915-1918: officers at La Pietra
5. 1919
6. 1920-1922
7. 1927: Theatricals in the gardens of Villa La Pietra in June
8. 1965: Villa La Pietra estate, Honolulu
9. 1965
10. Arthur Acton's family ancestors
B. Baby Books (III.B.1.-III.B.2.)
(Box 3)
These were compiled by HMA for HA and WA and are scrapbooks with annotations by HMA which also contain photographs. The pages of the albums have been numbered in pencil in square brackets by the processor to correspond with the detailed description of each album provided on a print-out kept together with the album (but not included in full in the Finding Aid).
1. Harold Acton
2. William Acton
C. Albums of Art works and places (III.C.1.-III.C.13.)
(Box 3-6)
These historic albums with photographs pasted on to the pages consist of commercially produced prints of places and art works in Italy and the rest of Europe (some by famous photographers such as Carlo Naya of Venezia and Giorgio Sommer of Napoli and Alinari of Firenze). The prints of places include some of towns and monuments in Germany and France later destroyed in the War. The albums have only been described summarily since they are almost certainly not unique.
1. Veronese frescoes at Villa Maser, taken by C. Naya, 1873
2. 'Italia' circa 1870s
3. Album belonging to Hortense Mitchell, September 1888
4. Album belonging to Hortense Mitchell, September 1890
5. Album belonging to Marguerite Mitchell, 1891
6. Album belonging to Marguerite Mitchell, 1891
7. Album made in Chicago, 1892
8. Album made in Chicago ca. 1892
9. Album made in Chicago ca. 1892
10. Album belonging to Harold Acton, 1911
11. Album belonging to William Acton, 1912
12. Album (empty) of Guy Mitchell's Villa Passerini
13. Album (empty) of Villa La Pietra Gardens, around 1930
The following albums have been excluded from Series III and filed elsewhere: WA's exhibition in London in 1937 (in I.D.3.); Four albums with prints of the gardens of Villa La Pietra (in II.A.10); Guy Mitchell's Villa Passerini, Firenze (in V.A.1.); Albums of villas on Villa La Pietra estate (in II.C.); Albums of postcards (in VI.E.); Peking Opera, China (in VII.F.)
Series IV: Works of Art
A. This series is currently being processed and is unavailable for consultation.
B. Art objects (with locations) (IV.B.1.-IV.B.11.)
(Box 14-24)
This series includes all works of art where the location is identified. They are filed by medium (in the same order as IV.A. above) and within that sub-series, topographically. These were presumably collected by the Actons for study purposes, and include many Alinari and Brogi prints. See also Series VI.B.
1. Paintings and drawings and prints
i. Italy
ii. Europe
iii. USA and Canada
2. Painted decoration
3. Frescoes
4. Sculpture
i. Italy
ii. Europe
iii. USA and Canada
5. Decorative sculpture and carving (mostly in interiors)
i. Italy
ii. Europe
iii. USA and Canada
6. Garden statues
7. Garden or exterior decorative sculpture
8. Decorative arts
9. Textiles
10. Furniture
11. Works of art used as illustrations in HA's published works
C. Interiors (IV.C.1.-IV.C.4.)
(Box 25)
Filed topographically.
1. Italy
2. Europe
3. USA
4. unidentified
D. Private Collections (IV.D.)
(Box 26-27)
Filed alphabetically by owner. Includes both identified and unidentified art works. These include only those prints with annotations which identify them as works in private collections at the time of the Actons (although there must be numerous other art objects in IV.A.-IV.C. which have at one time or another been in private hands). In some cases the processor has noted the present location when known.
Series V: Places
A. Italian Villas and Gardens (V.A.1.-V.A.3.)
(Box 1-2)